The general approach of how I think
about writing is just to say something
that people already say. We'll start
with the chorus first. Oh, that could be
cool, too. If I sing up and the melody
goes up, there's some in it catchiness
attached to that. The same kind of
rhythm, but like one tiny little change.
It's very
syncop and I want something to balance
it out. This is what happened with We
Don't Talk Anymore and that vocal ended
up being in the actual song.
So the general approach of how I think
about writing in general um is just to
say something that people already say.
Um as songwriters, as artists, as
producers, uh our goal is to help people
who don't do that for a profession to
fill in the blank for them. uh to make
something that they want to say to
somebody uh a bit easier by showing them
a song, by maybe showing them the song
that we're writing right now, the song
that you're writing, the one that I'm
writing. We want to uh as artists
because it's what we are artists, we
want to make people's lives easier um by
having by using like a song assistant
method. And uh that's why I always kind
of think about uh that's why I always
pay attention to what people say in
conversation. Uh because people might
inadvertently say something really dope
and it might turn into a cool lyric. And
I think I was kind of riffing on
something in the last lesson. I had like
a little sentence pop up um in my head.
We'll see if that still works. I need a
little refresh. I might need to play
this track a couple times. But um we'll
start with the chorus first and then
build around that. That's what I usually
do. come up with the chore first and
then all the stuff surrounding it. I
always start out by listening at a very
low volume. I don't want to kill my
ears. Oh yeah, I
[Music]
remember.
Right. So, I have something in mind.
This is the verse section right here,
but I'm not going to focus on that right
now. This is the chorus coming up right
here. I'm going to focus on that.
[Music]
I'm for sure changing that snare, but
it's good to hear it just for the rhythm
right now. Okay, so what I would usually
do, and I'd recommend you to do the
same, um, I have this little record
track right here. I'll make it bigger to
put some emphasis on it. Um, I make it
red and yellow and uh red for record.
And the only thing I have on here right
now, um, my vocal chain is an 1176 going
through a uh, well, it used to be a TD2.
Now it's a it's a Neve kind of
situation. Um, I'm not even going to
pretend I know all the ins and outs of
that compressor. It just makes my voice
sound good. This is a Telephunin. I
usually use um a little cheaper handheld
mic, but might as well use a really nice
one if it's right here in front of me. I
I'm very insecure about my voice to be
completely honest. And um I try and put
as much stuff on it right away. Like I
know for like Alicia Keys for example is
an amazing singer, a way better singer
than me and sings with absolutely
nothing. No reverb, no autotune or
anything. Um I do the opposite because
I'm not as good of a singer. So, I need
to hear my voice kind of perfect because
I guess it's my perfect pitch, too. Um,
if I hear one wrong note, I'll just get
discouraged and think the melody's bad.
So, on the first channel strip here,
I'll put the autotune to classic mode
and turn the retune speed uh all the way
up to zero. Um, so it sounds like a
super robot and put it into classic
mode, of course. Um, D flat major. Like
I said, this song is in D flat major.
Um, I'll
probably let's put a little reverb on
here. So, I put
it I make it
super super tuned because I know it's
not going to end up sounding like that,
but in my mind it's honestly I just saw
Esther Dean track her vocals like that
back in 2015 when I worked with her and
I just have done it ever since. And it
just sounds like it sounds like a final
vocal even though it's super robotic and
you know that there's room for
improvement. So that's why I do
it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um I also
have a CLA 76 on here just because it's
low latency.
[Music]
Um I do it just like that. I can turn
the input up and squash the vocal a
little bit. It's the what's going to
inspire a lot of melodies out of me is
uh knowing that it sounds like
like what's the best way to say this?
Like super squashed, but like not too
squashed. Uh and like I want to hear a
lot of processing on my voice. Let's
throw an eighth note delay on here, too.
Check. Check. Check. Check. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So, I have this melody. When I was
making the track, this melody kind of
just reared its head um uh while I was
making it. And it's just a it's just a
fifth above the D flat. So, starting on
an A flat. And in my mind, this chorus
when with when the vocal is completely
finished would have a slightly stacked
Tears for Fears kind of sounding vocal
versus
a be
like uh and I would stack that kind of
like midsy headone airy voice uh like
maybe four times. I can show you how I
how I do that. But, uh, I'll make the
demo, uh, I'll sometimes tune the demo
and make it sound perfect because then I
can I just like enjoy it more when I bop
around and listen to it in the car. It
sounds like a almost finished product
even though it's not. Um, so let's
listen to this chorus one more
[Music]
time. Got to turn it
up. Just going to turn that synth down a
little bit, too.
[Music]
So, the lyric I had in mind was why you
got to get why you got to go and get my
hopes up. And we'll figure out what why
my brain wanted me to do that, but it
just it also sounds good off the tongue.
Why you got to go and get my hopes
up? I don't know what it means
yet. Why you got to go and get my Hold
on.
[Music]
Oh, oh, that could be cool,
too. Okay, something I love. Okay, pause
real quick. Something I love doing
is whatever the lyric is, and it doesn't
have to work out like this all the time,
but whatever the lyric is, um, if
something's mirroring that in the
melody, so if the lyric is I don't know,
I think the lyric in this song is going
to be why you got to go and get my hopes
up. if because it's a it it checks a
couple boxes for me. It's something that
people say, "Oh, you got my hopes up."
Uh, and I think it would be really cool
if the melody went up when I go up, too.
So, if I sing up and the melody goes up,
there's some inate catchiness attached
to that. Let's see if it sounds good. I
could be completely off, but I don't
think I
[Music]
am. We just got to get every note
perfectly.
get closer to it.
[Music]
And that would be stacked, too. But why
you got to go and get
my hopes up? That's kind of dope.
Um, okay. So, I'll record I'll I'll turn
the autotune a little bit down on the
track that I drag it
to. It's just for recording purposes.
I don't want that up to be not as whiny.
I want it to
be my
[Music]
kind of sang it the same way, but it's
cleaner. Uh, do you
Okay, so this is the most important
part. I'll take the I'll unarm the track
for a second. Um, on the theme of going
slow and methodical with everything, I
will
up a little bit.
Why you got to go and get my hopes up? I
want that to be on the grid. And I know
it's a demo vocal, but
sounds pretty on the grid. Actually, I
might just take this and just drag it.
And maybe this one, too. Why? You got
to Why you got to gota gota Why you got
to go? And the Y just over to the left a
little bit.
Give my Let me put it on the grid. See
where that 16th note is? Yeah, I can
drag this over to the left a little bit.
It's just It's
so satisfying just having the silly demo
vocal just being so in pocket.
Even
trim this
down. This is what happened with with We
Don't Talk Anymore. And that vocal ended
up being in the actual song. So, you
never know. I don't think this one is,
but maybe it will be. I don't know.
I want to get get my
Just take some space out. Just there's
something rhythmic about it. I don't
know. Got to go and get my hopes. Got to
go and get my go and get my hopes up.
Got to go and get my get my kind of take
this one out. This is what I do for
every song.
It's barely noticeable.
Just a little cut right here, too. So,
it just like impacts it lands.
Just that up. Bring it over a little
bit. So it's
I want to hear it with
some more tune.
[Music]
Something like simple like Okay, so
that's the tag right there. I got to go
and get
my
d and I'll copy and paste that one since
I spent so much time making it good.
Oops. Hold on. Over
one. Boom.
[Applause]
I hate that snare. I got to mute that
snare. No production right now, but I'm
just
so much better. Okay, sorry.
Okay, so let's do the B melody right
now. This might be a little rough, but
let's
see. And make me think from the and make
and why you got to go and get my hopes
up and make me think you wanted me from
the beginning. Make me think you did. I
mean, I know you wouldn't say make me
think you did want me from the
beginning, but like it it's kind of a
weird way to say it. I don't know. could
change, but we're going to get the
melody
[Music]
and why you got to go and get my
Why you got to go and get my
Ooh, okay. Dragged it. and make me think
you did and then and make me think you
did me from what you did.
Ooh, maybe I go up on that.
[Music]
I'm going to bring the compressor of
this LA2A. I love this by UuAD. Just
make it a little more squashed.
I should probably here I'll I'll show
you what my chain is right now. So,
obviously I have my record track right
here and then I record everything here
and then drag it down to this chorus
track. I just have it in my template
because I always start with the chorus.
Um, this just take a little lows out.
Uh, whatever the hell this thing is.
This is like a What even is this? See, I
don't even like know like my engineer at
Ben helped me set this up. I don't know.
It's like a compressor or something like
that. This is a
DSER. This is a great compressor. Kind
of just like I recorded a very low. I I
gain staged it a little bit, but like
this kind of just rounds everything out
and makes it nice and pleasant. And uh
Zed told me to do this. Put a little bit
of uh widening delay on the vocal. This
is the difference here. If I take it
off,
if you don't want to take the time to
stack a bunch of vocals, you just put
the turn this up here. It sounds like
this.
And this is just about kind of blending
it and making it sound not You don't
want it to be like like that. That's
annoying. So, you just bring it up like
I'm going to take a little
bit. I'm going to drag these here. And I
want less
delay. Again, it's not a race. It's
better to just kind of move slow and
thoughtful.
I don't even want the fourth delay, but
I'm going to keep it there anyway
because it does something. Why you got
to go and get my hopes up and make me
think
I'm going to sing that a little bit
softer. And then go and get my and make
me think you
did. And make me
think from the
[Music]
beginning. Yeah, I think I'm going to
go B
[Applause]
flat because it's about
like I don't know. It just feels nice
going to the B flat twice there. Let's
see. Get my
[Music]
Yeah, it's catchier. Let me just get
that a little bit better.
[Music]
Take this down here. Drag it down.
there. Blend.
Clean.
[Applause]
Okay. So, maybe the same kind of rhythm,
but like one tiny little change. Why you
got to go and get my hopes up and make
me think you did want me from the
beginning?
[Music]
Uh
um
Okay, that's better. There's a little
[Music]
like Okay, so I'm not going to figure
out that lyric right now, but I know I
want that pocket and that rhythm because
I haven't had that straight. It's very
syncopated D and I want something to
balance it out. Uh, so it's like m 75%
syncopated this B part and then you put
them uh you give it a little bit of uh
the straight notes like a da da da da
eighth notes and then you're back at the
hook again like the uh the tagline
rather.
I'm just going to say like something
random right now. It's just like sounds
like words but not really.
I went down
and leave me.
I don't know what I'm saying.
[Music]
Uh, come on. Why you got to go? Oh,
that's cool. The people would say that.
Come on. Why you got to go and get get
my hopes up? Leave me on. Come on. All
you got to
do. Come on. You got to leave me. Come
on. Why you got to go and get my Okay.
So, you do this. I feel like this would
be on
a like. Okay. So, I have these
background this background bus here. I
Let's see what that that come on sounds
like as a response rather than actually
on the lead vocal. I think it'd be kind
of a nice ear break. So, let's kind of
take this up a little
bit. Definitely need some tune on
there. Just put it on every first
section of the channel.
[Music]
Just have a bit of fun with it. Take a
Valhalla. And, you know, Max does this a
lot.
uh size down.
Let's see.
Uh
and we're just going to stack that right
now and have it like uh not on the lead,
but in the background as like kind of a
response. Come on. It's like you're
having like a conversation uh with one
voice.
I'll back the tune off that a little
bit.
[Music]
So, this is what I usually do on a set
of four background vocals. I have the
come on, the very frontal nasely kind of
thing. Um, and then, uh, Babyface always
told me to do this to layer it with a
like a barely audible whisper and then a
slightly, uh, more noty whisper. So,
we'll do the slightly more noty whisper.
That'll This is what this is right here.
So, instead of come on, you do come on.
I guess it's falsetto would be an easy
way to say it. Just lay it in, but like
morphing your voice to make it just
sound like to support the other vocal.
me. Come on. Come
[Music]
on. Come on. Come
on. Come on.
That sounds kind of nice. Okay. And one
more.
[Music]
Might not even need the little whisper.
But we'll do it anyway since I said
it. Come on. Just that. Come on.
Because it sounds like a
crowd. You're doing that.
Um maybe on those
whispers. Just take a simple EQ for one
band. Just do a highp pass.
Super
airy. Sorry, I know that metronome is
annoying.
Group them together and kind of turn it
down and blend them in.
This is without it.
This is with it.
Adds something which is pretty cool.
for fun. Let's stack that. Why you got
to go and get my hopes up? I'm going to
And by the way, I'm going to res all of
this, but it's just so fun again to have
a demo vocal that sounds like almost
done even though it's not.
Okay, let's see him
[Music]
cuz then I kind of have like an outline
of how I'm really going to record it.
Like I'll know that I'm going to stack
why you got to go and get my hopes up
and maybe leave this next part as a solo
vocal.
[Music]
Why you got to go and get my hopes up
and make
me Why you got to go and get my hopes up
and make me think you
[Music]
did my
Okay, one more.
Maybe one more whisper too.
[Music]
By the way, I do this to hear myself a
little bit better. Um, sometimes I'll
even go off pitch if I am too much in
headphone world. So, I can still feel
like the the resonance in my voice by
just letting one ear loose.
[Music]
And if I were recording a real vocal, I
would then uh vocal line everything and
make everything super tight, but we
don't need to do that right now.
I may be going back on my idea that
everything has to be super tuned. It
kind of sounds better.
I like that better. I think that's
better. Get my hopes up and make me
think you did want me from the
beginning. Understand? Leave me on. Come
on. Why you got to go? That's kind of
hard. Hold on. Let's put this on
a
Let's Let's do
this, man. Got to go. Let's drag these
down here. Just I love separation and I
love being able to like change something
independently.
So, we're just gonna do this
this. Okay.
Because I don't want as much reverb on
these right here.
[Music]
So, I'll just use the proper reverb.
understand.
[Music]
Now I can take these here and drag them
back to where they once were.
Okay, so now we're at the second half of
the chorus. Um, I want a different rhyme
scheme because every time I do a chorus,
I think it should sound like a a roller
coaster. Like when I used to go to Six
Flags, like I would want to just ride
the roller coaster over and over again
because there was just something to look
forward to. You want the listener to
have something to uh look forward to. So
if you have the same rhyming scheme,
it's just going to kind of be monotonous
and maybe they won't play the song
again. You want them to play as much as
possible, especially in today's
streaming environment.
and make me think you did want me from
the beginning. Understand? Leave me on.
Come on. You got to go and get my hopes
up. Uh, so my last rhyme was make me
think you
did. There you go. But I'm also kind of
thinking of like what could you say? You
don't want to just make it complete
babble, but hint at some
words. Make me think you did want me
from the beginning. Understand? Leave me
on. Come on. Why you got to go and get
[Music]
my Why don't you go like
I got to fit a little Y.
Nice. Drag that little Y in there.
Come on. Why you got to go and get my
hopes up?
I want to rear and disappear. Oh yeah,
you could say something like why you got
to go and get my hopes up and make it
seem like you're always going to be here
and then one day you just go up and
disappear or something like that. I
don't know if that's like Cash would be
able to like help me kind of like bring
it home, but like the idea is there
because that's what someone would do
like in a relationship like I'm sure you
or some I've definitely gone through
like you know I've been really excited
um about like being with somebody and
maybe she has eyes on somebody else and
completely you know doesn't know how to
tell me so trying to just like you know
what's the term ghost get ghosted that's
happened to me before um and I get my
hopes up I was looking forward I was
planning out dinners I was uh you know
thinking about what I was going to wear
what I was going to smell like or
something. I don't know. It's real. Like
everything that you put into your art
should be 100% real. Um it should be the
truth because uh even if somebody
listens to this and they're like, "Oh, I
don't like this. This sounds like a
typical Charlie song." It's like they
can have that opinion, but they can't
deny that it's not the truth. Uh and
I've written songs that maybe weren't
the truth. And those didn't resonate at
all with people because people are
smart. They can tell uh what is truthful
and what is not. And this is the truth.
I've felt this emotion before. Maybe you
have as well. Maybe you want to look
forward to feeling this emotion in some
sick way. I don't know. Uh but it's art.
It's fun.
[Music]
Why you got to go and get
my Okay, I'll just like say some babble
and then figure it out later.
[Music]
I want to hold on.
Disappear. I want to end on disappear.
Okay.
[Music]
understand
and that's when you do the little melody
change.
together and then one day I
disappear and one day you just
disappear. I would say one day you just
disappear but it doesn't like fall off
the tongue. Really super nice. And one
day you just disappear. Like you want it
to be as easy to sing along to as
possible. That's why I'm okay with
babble for now.
day.
Let's do that then.
[Music]
And then one day you disappear. Not
perfect, but good for now.
[Music]
And then you go and then you go and
disappear.
And then you go and disappear. Oh,
that's nice.
And then you go and disappear. But okay,
so one, but I don't want to say go
because I say why I got to go and get my
hopes up. There's too many goes. So
So you're just kind of jumbling in your
mind like what else could be said
[Music]
there? I just say wanna for now.
[Applause]
[Music]
Okay, sick. Let me see if that makes if
that's cohesive the beginning of it.
You understand? Leave me on. Come on.
[Music]
I got to sing it the same way that See
how this sounds different than I got to
sing it like this.
So understand. Okay.
Then you want to But then you want to
disappear.
And then you But then
you disappear.
It's kind of dope actually. But then you
want to disappear could actually be a
real lyric.
Then you want to disappear.
And how did I do the
[Music]
and that's going to rhyme. That's going
to mirror that exactly that rhyme
scheme.
understanding. So, we have to figure out
like another word that
has songis.
[Music]
Not this. This is kind of cheesy, but
like it sounds good. Keep me up till the
dawn. Come on.
[Music]
And then you do come on. And then now
we're starting to have a well-rounded
chorus. Let me just copy paste these
couple elements here.
Got to sing that better.
[Music]
actually hate that part, but it sounds
good for now.
[Music]
Okay, so I paste the commands now.
Good chorus should literally just mirror
itself.
Now I know.
And what's really cool
[Music]
You got to go and get my hopes.
Okay. Okay. So, this is the scratch
course we have so far.
Leave me on. Come on. Why you got to go
and get my hopes up and lonely like an
ear? Then you want to disappear. Keep me
up till the dawn. Come on. Why you got
to go and get my
Okay.
Maybe a
[Music]
post or we could be really boss going
into Okay, so let's figure out before we
figure out the form, let's figure out
what the verse melody is going to be.
Hey, hey, hey.